"Mercury in High Fructose Corn Syrup"
Whether you feed people honey,
table sugar,
or high-fructose corn syrup,
you see similarly negative
metabolic effects.
A meta-analysis
of all such studies
found there didn't appear
to be any difference
between the negative effects
of high-fructose corn syrup
and table sugar on body fat,
blood pressure, blood sugars,
triglycerides, or cholesterol.
But high-fructose corn syrup
did appear to be
more pro-inflammatory.
One thing that sets apart
corn syrup from sugar
is mercury,
detected in about half
the samples
of high-fructose corn syrup
analyzed.
In terms of diet, mercury is
routinely detected in fish,
but it's also found
in other meat like poultry
because farmers routinely feed
fishmeal to chickens,
but how is mercury
getting into corn syrup?
Everything you wanted to know
but were afraid to ask.
It turns out mercury can enter
the corn sweetener market line
in one of two ways:
the use
of mercury-processed chemicals
in the manufacturing process
or the intentional addition
of mercury-containing chemicals.
Either way, does it actually
make it to the consumer?
Researchers looked
at 50 different brands of foods
containing corn syrup,
from soda pop to Pop-Tarts,
Yoplait yogurt, jelly.
The results?
About 30 percent
were contaminated
with detectable levels
of mercury.
Enough to be harmful?
With the average
daily consumption of corn syrup,
and how much mercury
they found,
the potential average
daily total mercury exposure
from high-fructose corn syrup
could range from zero
to 28 micrograms.
This range can be compared
to the range
of total mercury exposure
from those silvery dental
amalgam mercury fillings
we get for cavities.
Canada and other countries
recommend
against the use
of mercury amalgam
in pregnant women or children,
as does the United States
as of 2020.
Of course, a single can of tuna
can have as much mercury
as a whole cup (240 ml)
of high-fructose corn syrup.
But still,
we probably shouldn't let
our kids become
children of the corn.
Given its mercury
contamination,
one could argue
that high-fructose corn syrup
is worse than sugar.
But both are bad for us.
They're both
just empty calories,
calories with zero nutrition.
Check out this classic
sugar industry ad:
"If sugar is so fattening,
how come so many kids
are thin?"
That certainly can't
be said anymore.
The tagline?
"Sugar.
It's not just good flavor;
sugar is good food."
As unbelievable
as that one was,
this is my favorite:
Mary is a busy girl.
"She needs sugar in her life.
For energy.
She needs energyless,
artificial sweeteners
like a turtle
needs a seat belt."
"...18 calories per teaspoon
and it's all energy."
That's the problem!
Only the sugar industry could
take its greatest weakness--
empty calories--
and try to spin it
into something good.
"Note to Mothers: Play it safe
with your young ones—
make sure they get sugar
every day."